<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
        <channel>
                <title>Rodrigo Davies</title>
                <description>A blog about how technology and media impact communities and governments, and the ways they are adapting to new challenges and opportunities.</description>
                <link>http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog</link>
                <atom:link href="http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
                
                        <item>
                                <title>A New Way to Invest in Communities</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/ggb.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past couple of years I&amp;#39;ve been thinking about how to bring the energy, potential and ambition of donation/reward crowdfunding to community development and civic engagement. I was lucky to be an early employee of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spacehive.com&quot;&gt;Spacehive&lt;/a&gt;, one of the first movers in the space, I put together the first &lt;a href=&quot;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2434615&quot;&gt;study of the field&lt;/a&gt; (with the help of &lt;a href=&quot;http://civiccrowdfunding.com&quot;&gt;Ethan&lt;/a&gt; and others at MIT), and I got to watch as the idea of civic crowdfunding caught the attention of the media, researchers, and finally, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/news/prime-minister-hails-the-rise-of-civic-crowdfunding&quot;&gt;heads of state&lt;/a&gt;. I got to watch some incredible people &lt;a href=&quot;http://spacehive.com/glyncochcc&quot;&gt;make change for their neighborhoods&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://catarse.me/pt/pimpmycarroca&quot;&gt;their communities&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there were two questions that often gave me pause. First, should we be funding civic projects through philanthropy, and does the success of that undermine public investment? Second, is it realistic to expect philanthropic crowds to raise the large sums that are often necessary to improve a community&amp;#39;s quality of life? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first question is a judgement call for which I&amp;#39;ve seen persuasive arguments on both sides. On the second question, I&amp;#39;ve seen very few cases that persuade me that the answer is yes. That&amp;#39;s not to say donation/reward civic crowdfunding doesn&amp;#39;t have a bright future in some respects. It has proven itself to be a robust way to produce small-scale change, especially in urban communities. As I&amp;#39;ve argued many times before, if non-profits start to take donation/reward crowdfunding seriously as a tactic, it has the potential to transform that sector and energize a whole new generation of small-dollar philanthropists. I will continue to work with and advise organizations who are considering donation-based civic crowdfunding for the right projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are other methods of financing community development that can give a much stronger &amp;#39;yes&amp;#39; to that second question, the question of scale. One of those is a very old form of crowd-based finance: municipal bonds. For just over two centuries, U.S. cities have been using them to finance critical improvements, from transport infrastructure, to schools, to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://goldengatebridge.org/research/BondMeasure.php&quot;&gt;Golden Gate Bridge&lt;/a&gt;. Municipal bonds give individuals the opportunity to invest in improvements to their city, while receiving predictable, tax-free returns every year, and, at the end of the bond (often 5-10 years), the individual gets his or her money back. They don&amp;#39;t offer the theoretically sky-high returns of stocks, but they do offer tax-efficient returns at very low risk (the default rate on municipal bonds is close to 1 in 1,000). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Municipal bonds should be easy, sleep-at-night investments that allow you to contribute to your community directly. The problem is, they&amp;#39;re not. At this moment in time, buying a municipal bond is complicated and expensive, in the U.S. &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.iriomk.com/post/104125235983/a-melhor-forma-de-nao-investir-em-titulos-publicos&quot;&gt;and elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;. Those who have wealth and the right broker are buying them, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bondbuyer.com/news/washington-taxation/sen-coburn-eliminate-the-muni-tax-exemption-1068624-1.html&quot;&gt;benefiting disproportionately&lt;/a&gt; because the market is effectively closed to the average person. People are starting to realize that they&amp;#39;re missing out, and when cities do open up their bond issuances, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.denverpost.com/news/ci_26272746/denvers-500-mini-bonds-sell-out-first-hour&quot;&gt;they sell out fast&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;re heading towards an inflection point, and I&amp;#39;m certainly not the only one to have realized that. &lt;a href=&quot;http://neighbor.ly&quot;&gt;Neighbor.ly&lt;/a&gt;, which was one of the pioneers in the donation-based civic crowdfunding space, is building a platform to allow individuals and households to invest directly in their cities by buying bonds. So I&amp;#39;ve decided to join the team as Head of Product to help make that happen. I&amp;#39;m taking leave from my research because I think we&amp;#39;re at a critical moment in deciding the future path of community development, and I want to be in the front seat with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://neighbor.ly/about&quot;&gt;fantastic team&lt;/a&gt; that &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/luminopolis&quot;&gt;Jase&lt;/a&gt; has put together. It&amp;#39;s also a fun return to a subject I once spent a lot of time on: my first job out of college was reporting on government bonds and currency markets for Bloomberg News in London. So all that studying of yield curves and ratings scales is coming in very handy once again, a decade later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From now on on this blog, you&amp;#39;ll be reading more about how municipal bonds work (and don&amp;#39;t work), and soon we&amp;#39;ll be giving you the chance to invest directly in your community through Neighborly. Come and join us on this new path.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2014 01:00:01 -0800</pubDate>
                                <link>http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/12/18/a-new-way-to-invest-in-communities.html</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/12/18/a-new-way-to-invest-in-communities.html</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Three Provocations for Civic Crowdfunding</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/3.png&quot; alt=&quot;http://www.fotopedia.com/users/R53-8VoCz0M&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week I&amp;#39;m in Daegu, Korea, and on Thursday (23rd October) will be giving a talk at the annual &lt;a href=&quot;http://ir15.aoir.org/&quot;&gt;Association of Internet Researchers conference (AoIR)&lt;/a&gt;, titled &amp;quot;Three Provocations for Civic Crowdfunding.&amp;quot; If you&amp;#39;re in Daegu, do stop by the session or find me around the event. If you&amp;#39;re not in Daegu, I&amp;#39;ll update this post with my slides before Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m excited to be part of a panel called &amp;quot;Commodification and Crowdsourcing&amp;quot;, with &lt;a href=&quot;http://wishcrys.com/&quot;&gt;Crystal Abidin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://dbrabham.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;Daren Brabham&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wlu.ca/homepage.php?grp_id=608&amp;amp;f_id=35&quot;&gt;Andrew Herman&lt;/a&gt;. Daren is one of the few other researchers I&amp;#39;ve found who is paying attention to the sociological aspects of crowdfunding, and he&amp;#39;s going to be talking about the impact of crowdfunding discourse on public funding for the arts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since AoIR format is short papers, I&amp;#39;ve included the full text below. An extended version will hopefully be appearing in print over the next few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Three Provocations for Civic Crowdfunding: AoIR 15, Daegu, Korea&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rapid rise of crowdfunding in the past five years, most prominently among US-based platforms such as Kickstarter and IndieGoGo, has begun to attract the attention of a wide range of scholars, policymakers and practitioners. As the industry evolves, it is developing a range of specialist sub-genres and platforms, from politics to manufacturing. This paper considers civic crowdfunding – the use of crowdfunding for projects that produce community or quasi-public assets – and argues that its emergence demands a fresh set of questions and approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scholarly analyses of crowdfunding to date have centered on fields such as investment finance, and Computer-Supported Co-operative Work (CSCW). While these inquiries have begun to build a frameworks for understanding the dynamics of the fundraising process and participants&amp;#39; motivations, there is yet to be substantial work considering the socio-political context and broader implications of crowdfunding. These questions are necessarily more pressing and contested when considering the use of crowdfunding for civic projects. The sub-field of `civic crowdfunding&amp;#39; as an application of the model is yet to be defined by academic researchers. The use of the term can be traced to 2012, and is used by platforms such as Spacehive and Neighbor.ly (Davies 2014a). This paper uses a mixed-methods case study approach to highlight and analyze critical cases in civic crowdfunding. It draws on quantitative analysis of project fundraising data drawn from four platforms (Citizinvestor, IOBY, Neighbo.ly and Spacehive), participant interviews and discourse analysis of projects&amp;#39; promotional material. In so doing it posits three provocations for the future study of civic crowdfunding. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, to what extent is civic crowdfunding participatory? It can be a truly organic mechanism that is a new tool available to activists. In Sao Paulo, Brazil, the graffiti artist Mundano raised $27,000 on the Catarse platform in May 2012 --- twice the campaign&amp;#39;s original target --- to paint the carts of waste pickers, as a means of highlighting their contribution to the city&amp;#39;s environmental sustainability and advocating for new labor protections for them. The idea that crowdfunding is a form of participation as well as a funding mechanism is salient since civic crowdfunding has emerged after a decade of experimentation with symbolic money as a representation of agency through participatory budgeting, most prominently in Brazil and New York City. But most crowdfunding platforms do not support the kind of deliberative process that would be expected in a participatory democratic structure: by the time a campaign is published on a platform, the idea is expected to be fully formed. Furthemore, since donations vary in size and offer differential agencies, the field is open to the charge that it may become dominated by resourced interests. Several of the largest civic crowdfunding campaigns to date have drawn the majority of their funding not from a high volume, low-donation value crowd, but from wealthier donors. For example, Kansas City&amp;#39;s B-Cycle program, partially crowdfunded on Neighbor.ly, drew 99% of its funding from six backers who donated more than $5,000 each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, does civic crowdfunding exacerbate or reduce economic inequality? At the case level, there are clear examples of underserved and privileged communities benefiting from civic crowdfunding in very different ways. In Glyn Coch, South Wales, a community with chronic unemployment and resource challenges, local organizers raised $49,000 to fill a gap in funding for a new community center, most of which was funded by government grants. By contrast, in October 2013, three wealthy suburban communities in Oakland, CA, raised $50,000 on the CrowdTilt platform to crowdfund private security patrols. The campaigns, which emerged within a few days of each other, demonstrated the risk of a &amp;#39;contagion effect&amp;#39; through which resourced communities could use civic crowdfunding campaigns from other localities as templates for building their replacement public services. At the platform level there are more ambiguous indicators with respect to equity. New York and Miami-based platform IOBY is the only platform that explicitly recruits projects from underserved communities. Early findings suggest that IOBY projects occur in neighborhoods with slightly higher poverty rates, but the difference is marginal (Goodspeed and Davies 2014). Citizinvestor finds in its own data that there is no correlation between the likelihood of a project occurring in a neighborhood and that neighborhood&amp;#39;s average household income. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, does civic crowdfunding support or undermine the role of public institutions? In many cases the link between civic crowdfunding and weakened institutions is direct: The bankrupt city of Central Falls, Rhode Island, crowdfunded $20,000 to pay for recycling facilities in Jenks park in November 2013, explicitly citing its financial distress as a motivating factor. Around one in ten projects in the dataset makes reference to shortfalls in public funding, and Brabham has argued that the success of crowdfunding is likely to be a disincentive for public investment in the arts in the future (Davies 2014b, Brabham 2012). Yet on the other hand, civic crowdfunding can also be framed as a mechanism that expands the range of public-private partnerships that are possible, since government can partner with crowdfunded groups. Parklets, a system of allowing individuals and groups to create temporary installations in parking spaces, is one public-private framework that has benefited from crowdfunding. Eleven parklets have been successfully crowdfunded via Kickstarter since April 2012, in Oakland, Philadelphia, San Francisco, Seattle and Vancouver, raising a total of $100,853. In August 2013, the City of San Francisco launched Living Innovation Zones, a program modeled on parklets that invites proposals for a series of underutilized spaces across the city, and encourages prospective groups to consider crowdfunding. Public-private opportunities that embrace crowdfunding as a potential tool are nascent, but are gaining in popularity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of these three provocations is highly context-specific and as yet the signals from the available data and reported cases are mixed and often conflicting. Nevertheless, they underscore the importance of approaching civic crowdfunding as a socio-politically located and contested phenomenon, and offer pathways for researchers to begin to critically analyze and define the field. Future research work on civic crowdfunding that considers its institutional and political context is likely to be highly generative across disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brabham, Daren (2012). Crowdsourcing. Cambridge: MIT Press. Print.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Citizinvestor (2014), &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.citizinvestor.com/post/76530391900/do-projects-in-rich-neighborhoods-perform-better-than&quot;&gt;Do projects in rich neighborhoods perform better than those in poorer neighborhoods?&lt;/a&gt; Citizinvestor blog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Davies, Rodrigo (2014a), Civic Crowdfunding: &lt;a href=&quot;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2434615&quot;&gt;Participatory Communities,  Entrepreneurs and the Political Economy of Place&lt;/a&gt;. Cambridge: MIT Masters Thesis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Davies, Rodrigo (2014b), Three Competing Visions of Civic Crowdfunding. Place, (Dis)place and Citizenship, Wayne State University. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Goodspeed, Robert, Davies, Rodrigo (2014). Civic Crowdfunding: A New Method of Creative Placemaking. Under review.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2014 12:30:01 -0700</pubDate>
                                <link>http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/10/21/three-provocations-for-civic-crowdfunding.html</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/10/21/three-provocations-for-civic-crowdfunding.html</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Crowdfunding Cities as Collaborative Innovation</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/merge.png&quot; alt=&quot;http://www.fotopedia.com/users/R53-8VoCz0M&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today at the Academy of Management&amp;#39;s Annual Meeting in Philadelphia some colleagues and I will be giving a panel titled &lt;a href=&quot;http://program.aom.org/2014/submission.asp?mode=ShowSession&amp;amp;SessionID=1026&quot;&gt;Towards Government 2.0: Open Data and Innovation through Cross-Sector Collaboration&lt;/a&gt;. We&amp;#39;re going to be talking about open data, building better and more open government services, and how to foster civic collaboration across sectors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately I won&amp;#39;t be at the meeting in person (I&amp;#39;m in the midst of relocating to San Francisco), so I&amp;#39;ve contributed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NbnQHKdIwLY&quot;&gt;a video&lt;/a&gt; in which I talk about some of the work I&amp;#39;ve done on crowdfunding in cities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m interested in how crowdfunding can be a means not just of getting something done (i.e. a funding mechanism), but a means of getting something done in a particular way: collaboratively. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crowd in a crowdfunding campaign collaborates ambiently – by contributing in the same place, they benefit from mutual awareness and together create a movement that has momentum. But in civic crowdfunding there&amp;#39;s also another layer of possible collaboration, between the crowd and cities, because cities are likely to have an interest in almost any project that provides a service to a local community. That interest could be regulatory (the city regulates the use of a particular kind of space or activity), or it could be participatory (the city wants to know what&amp;#39;s going on and to support good ideas). Those interests could be construed positively or negatively, depending on the relationship between the city and the project participants – the city could be perceived as supportive and welcoming, or heavy-handed and interfering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crowdfunding has the potential to help structure those relationships positively, if cities and project owners approach the project in the right way. The substance of my talk, which you can check out below, is to give four suggestions for how cities can frame structure their involvement in civic crowdfunding projects to deliver the best outcomes. You&amp;#39;ll also be able to read more on this in &lt;a href=&quot;http://rodrigodavies.com/civiccrowdfunding&quot;&gt;an upcoming collection I&amp;#39;m contributing to on Smarter Cities&lt;/a&gt;, edited by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.esade.edu/faculty/esteve.almirall&quot;&gt;Esteve Almirall&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://boydcohen.com&quot;&gt;Boyd Cohen&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/NbnQHKdIwLY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As ever, your comments and feedback are much appreciated. Now that I&amp;#39;m in the Bay Area, if you&amp;#39;re local and working on similar topics, please reach out. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2014 03:01:01 -0700</pubDate>
                                <link>http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/08/03/crowdfunding-cities-collaborative-innovation.html</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/08/03/crowdfunding-cities-collaborative-innovation.html</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>What's Crowdfunding (and What's Not)</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/lonely.png&quot; alt=&quot;http://www.fotopedia.com/users/R53-8VoCz0M&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I came across a fundraising campaign by a consortium of non-profits in the US earlier this year to raise money over a short period of time. Participating organizations were ranked in a public ranking, and competed for prizes based on the amount they raised and the number of donors they attracted. A running total of the overall amount donated was published on the site. The effort was fairly successful, and raised close to a million dollars for over 300 organizations. The most successful organization raised over $25,000, although one-fifth of participating organizations raised zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initiative was described to me as being similar to crowdfunding, likely because of its gamified flavor. Although the folks behind it weren&amp;#39;t using the language of crowdfunding, several observers were. But it wasn&amp;#39;t crowdfunding, and there are a number of important reasons why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I get into that, let&amp;#39;s be clear: I&amp;#39;m not making a point about the technical definition of the term &lt;em&gt;crowdfunding&lt;/em&gt;. My critique is not that this initiative missed many opportunities to create a compelling campaign that crowdfunders and crowdfunding platforms make use of every day. The following criticisms are not specific to this case, either. They&amp;#39;re common problems among inexperienced (and reluctant) online fundraisers, particularly in the non-profit space. That&amp;#39;s why I&amp;#39;m not going to name the initiative here, instead I&amp;#39;m going to refer to it as Acme Non-Profit Initiative. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the biggest problems I observed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There was no crowd&lt;/strong&gt;. One of the main distinguishing elements of crowdfunding is the mutual awareness of donors. It&amp;#39;s what reminds us that we&amp;#39;re not acting alone (breaking down &amp;#39;pluralistic ignorance&amp;#39;), and gives us a sense of belonging. Acme Non-Profit Initiative&amp;#39;s website did not show any identifying information about other donors, simply the numbers. It was not, as far as I can tell, able to interface with donors&amp;#39; Facebook and Twitter accounts directly to enable them to see which of their friends had already donated. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There were no projects&lt;/strong&gt;. The prompt for donation was a one paragraph description of the organization, with a selection of links. There was no clear sense of what projects the organizations were raising money for at this particular time, and what stage they were at. It&amp;#39;s not true that crowdfunding can never be used to pay for overhead costs. If these costs are given as part of a project budget, backers won&amp;#39;t flee. Backers understand that it costs money to keep the lights on, but they&amp;#39;re most interested what&amp;#39;s happening in the building. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There were no targets&lt;/strong&gt;. Besides a number of prizes given to the most successful organizations, there was no sense of what the organizations and the crowd should be aiming for. As a result, there were no metrics for success and no sense of achievement, no matter how well the initiative went. Having the courage to set a target and asking the crowd to help you reach it is part of the interaction and engagement that crowdfunding demands. You&amp;#39;re asking the crowd to take a risk with you by backing your project, and in return your organization is taking a risk by putting its goals and ideas out in public.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The donation data wasn&amp;#39;t transparent&lt;/strong&gt;. I found that the total fundraising numbers being reported didn&amp;#39;t correspond with the itemized data. I presume that&amp;#39;s because additional funds were raised during the initiative but given directly, instead of through the platforms. That&amp;#39;s not unusual, but it raises red flags with potential donors when organizations provide incomplete data. A simple line that explained that a certain percentage of funds were given directly or in person would be enough. Being loose with the published numbers undermines the credibility of the initiative and doesn&amp;#39;t meet the standards of transparency people rightly associate with crowdfunding. We should continue to demand that. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As crowdfunding increasingly becomes used as a catch-all term for all kinds of online fundraising, we&amp;#39;re in danger of missing the point. That danger particularly applies to organizations who already fundraise regularly, and may be under the impression that all they need to do to take advantage of crowdfunding is to digitize, verbatim, their existing processes. The history of technological change has taught us time after time that that won&amp;#39;t work. New technologies reshape and restructure processes and organizations, whether they like it or not. And, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.philanthropy.blogspot.com/2014/05/civil-society-is-missing-boat-on-issues.html&quot;&gt;as Lucy Bernholz put it recently&lt;/a&gt;, we&amp;#39;re foolish to think that non-profits will be any different. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it&amp;#39;s great to see so many innovative twists on the crowdfunding model emerge, we need to be sure that we&amp;#39;re not calling things crowdfunding that are really not worthy of the term – and then being disappointed when those initiatives don&amp;#39;t deliver the engagement their creators are hoping for. When done correctly, crowdfunding is bold, risky and open, and it demands those same qualities from backers and creators alike. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2014 02:01:01 -0700</pubDate>
                                <link>http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/06/06/whats-crowdfunding-and-whats-not.html</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/06/06/whats-crowdfunding-and-whats-not.html</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Civic Crowdfunding – Four Things We Know, Two Things We Don't</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/thesis.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2434615&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I&amp;#39;m capping &lt;a href=&quot;http://rodrigodavies.com/civiccrowdfunding/&quot;&gt;two years of studying the emergence of civic crowdfunding&lt;/a&gt; by submitting my master&amp;#39;s thesis to the MIT archives. Great thanks are due to the wonderful collaborators I&amp;#39;ve had the privilege of working with. I won&amp;#39;t name everyone here, but all of you folks will find your names in the Acknowledgments section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read &lt;a href=&quot;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2434615&quot;&gt;Civic Crowdfunding: Participatory Communities, Entrepreneurs and the Political Economy of Place&lt;/a&gt; in its entirety (173 pages) now, and if you do so, I&amp;#39;d love to hear your feedback. Before you get to that, though, here are some of the most important things I learned about civic crowdfunding, and a few thoughts on where we&amp;#39;re headed next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crowdfunding is everywhere. People are using it to fund watches, comic books, even famous film directors are doing it. In what is now a $6 billion industry globally, I think the most interesting, disruptive and exciting work that&amp;#39;s happening is in donation-based crowdfunding. That’s worth, very roughly, $1.2 billion a year worldwide per year. Within that subset, I’ve been looking at civic projects, people who are producing shared goods for a community or broader public. These projects build on &lt;a href=&quot;http://rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/04/28/the-digital-pollada-or-what-i-learned-about-crowdfunding-from-peruvian-chicken.html&quot;&gt;histories of community fundraising and resource pooling that long predate the Internet&lt;/a&gt;; what’s changed is that we’ve created a scalable, portable platform model to carry out these existing practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how is civic crowdfunding doing? When I started this project very few people were using that term. No one had done any aggregated data collection and published it. So I decided to take on that task. I collected data on 1224 projects between 2010 and March 2014, which raised $10.74 million in just over three years. I focused on seven platforms: Catarse (Brazil), Citizinvestor (US), Goteo (Spain), IOBY (US), Kickstarter (US), Neighbor.ly (US) and Spacehive (UK). I didn’t collect everything. There’s a new crowdfunding site every week that may or may not have a few civic projects on it. If you&amp;#39;re interested in my methodology, check out Chapter 2. I don’t pretend to have captured every civic project that has ever existed, but I&amp;#39;m working with a representative sample. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are four things I found out about civic crowdfunding. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Civic crowdfunding is small-scale but relatively successful, and it has big ambitions.&lt;/strong&gt; Currently the average civic crowdfunding project is small in scale: $6,357 is the median amount raised. But these civic projects seem to be doing pretty well. Projects tagged &amp;#39;civic&amp;#39; on Kickstarter, for instance, succeed 81% of the time. If Civic were a separate category, it would be Kickstarter’s most successful category. Meanwhile, most platform owners and some incumbent institutions see civic crowdfunding as a new mechanism for public-private partnerships capable of realizing large-scale projects. In a small minority of cases, such as the three edge-case projects I explored in Chapter 3 of my thesis, civic crowdfunding has begun to fulfill some of those ambitions. For the center of gravity to shift further in the direction of these potential outcomes, though, existing institutions, including government, large non-profits and the for-profit sector, will need to engage more comprehensively with the process. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Civic crowdfunding started as a hobby for green space projects by local non-profits, but larger organizations are getting involved.&lt;/strong&gt; Almost a third of campaigners are using civic crowdfunding platforms for park and garden-related projects (29%). Event-based projects, and education and training are also popular. Sports and mobility projects are pretty uncommon. The frequency of garden and park projects is partly because these projects are not capital intensive, and they&amp;#39;re uncontroversial. That&amp;#39;s also changing. Organizations from governments to corporations and large foundations, are exploring ways to support crowdfunding for &lt;a href=&quot;http://rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/03/24/hawaii-proposes-the-first-civic-crowdfunding-bill.html&quot;&gt;a much wider range of community-facing activities&lt;/a&gt;. Their modes of engagement include &lt;a href=&quot;http://rodrigodavies.com/blog/2013/07/23/four-roles-civic-organizations-can-play-in-crowdfunding.html&quot;&gt;publicizing campaigns, match-funding campaigns on an ad-hoc basis, running their own campaigns and even building new platforms from the ground up&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Civic crowdfunding is concentrated in cities (especially those where platforms are based).&lt;/strong&gt; The genre is too new to have spread very effectively, it seems. Five states account for 80% of the projects, and this is partly a function of where the platforms are located. New York, California are our top two, followed by Illinois and Oregon. We know there’s a strong trend towards big cities. It&amp;#39;s hard work for communities to use crowdfunding to get projects off the ground, especially when it&amp;#39;s an unfamiliar process. The platforms have played a critical role in building participants&amp;#39; understanding of crowdfunding and supporting them through the process. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Civic crowdfunding has the same highly unequal distributional tendencies as other crowd markets.&lt;/strong&gt; When we look at the size distribution of projects, the first thing we notice is something close to a Pareto distribution, or Long Tail. Most projects are small-scale, but a small number of high-value projects have taken a large share of the total revenue raised by civic crowdfunding. We shouldn’t be surprised by this. On Kickstarter most successful projects are between 5 and 10k, and 47% of civic projects I studied are in the same bracket. &lt;a href=&quot;http://rodrigodavies.com/blog/2013/11/21/spreading-the-crowdfunded-wealth.html&quot;&gt;The problem is that we tend to remember the outliers, such as Veronica Mars and Spike Lee – because they show what’s possible&lt;/a&gt;. But they are still the outliers. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, here are two things we don’t know. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Will civic crowdfunding deter public investment or encourage it?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Will civic crowdfunding widen wealth gaps?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don&amp;#39;t have enough high-quality data, and not enough time has passed, to answer these questions satisfactorily yet. There are some clues in the rhetoric people use, which I explore in Chapter 4 of my thesis, but &lt;a href=&quot;http://rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/03/23/is-civic-crowdfunding-participatory-citizenship-or-a-sign-of-institutions-in-decline.html&quot;&gt;they point in many different, contradictory directions&lt;/a&gt;. Nevertheless, there are concrete goals we can work towards to try and make the answers to those two questions positive ones for community development and society more broadly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communities and the groups that serve them, in the government and social sector, are in an important position to influence how crowdfunding evolves. It can just as easily become a part of the toolkit for community organizing and be a mechanism for getting resources to places where they’re needed as it can be to do the opposite. I’ve been involved as a workshop leader and advisor in trying to help support some of this activity, but we’re really just getting started. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To really understand what’s going on, especially over the longer term, we need better data. We need to know more precisely when projects are happening, if they’re succeeding, and by what measure. And we need to be able to know how what’s happening in crowdfunding relates to the other things we measure. We can’t build civic engagement and awareness on the back of bad data. This is something I’m actively working on with the platforms I’ve worked with. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we need more socially-grounded research in this space. It&amp;#39;s one of the things I&amp;#39;m going to be spending my time on at Stanford over the next five years. I&amp;#39;m excited about advancing qualitative inquiry to support the quantitative analysis we’re doing, research that helps us understand how crowdfunding is changing the ways that organizations and the people within them work. We know crowdfunding is not just a numbers game, it’s a very human and complex game, and I look forward to continuing to help us understand it better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://civic.mit.edu/blog/rodrigodavies/civic-crowdfunding-%E2%80%93-four-things-we-know-two-things-we-dont&quot;&gt;(Cross-posted at civic.mit.edu)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2014 04:15:01 -0700</pubDate>
                                <link>http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/05/09/civic-crowdfunding-four-things-we-know-two-things-we-dont.html</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/05/09/civic-crowdfunding-four-things-we-know-two-things-we-dont.html</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>The Digital Pollada, or What I Learned About Crowdfunding from Peruvian Chicken</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/chicken.png&quot; alt=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/izik/2610556819/&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a tradition in Peru called the &lt;em&gt;pollada&lt;/em&gt; – literally, a chicken party. These parties perform a very important social function. Say I’m about to have a child and I’m worried about how I’m going to pay education or healthcare bills. I hold a pollada to raise money by inviting friends and family around for chicken and beers, and selling tickets to the event. The tickets are usually priced fairly highly. The friends who come to my party are willing to pay more than they would normally, because they know they’re contributing to my family&amp;#39;s welfare. Together, we fund the future of my family’s education. And we eat. And we bond. We form our own little crowd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like web-based crowdfunding, the pollada is a clever framing of the process of bringing people together to collaborate on a project. Just like a public crowdfunding campaign, the high level of mutual visibility at a pollada – we&amp;#39;re contributing (and partying) side by side with each other – is critical to its success. That mutual visibility &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/matter/76d9913c6011&quot;&gt;breaks down &amp;quot;pluralistic ignorance&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;, the anxiety that we&amp;#39;re acting alone. It reinforces our sense of membership and produces the social benefits associated with belonging. One of the best explanations of these benefits is provided by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nyu.edu/projects/nissenbaum/papers/jopp_235.pdf&quot;&gt;Benkler and Nissenbaum&amp;#39;s work on commons-based peer production&lt;/a&gt;. Crowdfunding and the pollada most clearly convey what they call Cluster III benefits (benevolence, charity, generosity, altruism) and Cluster IV benefits (sociability, camaraderie, friendship, cooperation, civic virtue).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the pollada is an important reminder that mutual awareness is an essential aspect of crowdfunding. It is one of the few characteristics of crowdfunding that fundamentally differentiates it from individuated fundraising. Every website that includes a donation button is not a crowdfunding website, because you can&amp;#39;t form a crowd in which the members are entirely invisible to each other. Members may be anonymous, their locations may be dispersed or unknown, but their co-presence must be evident. A pollada is not a pollada if we&amp;#39;re all enjoying chicken on our own. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned about the pollada this past week when I visited Peru with some colleagues from MIT, and used it as a way to contextualize crowdfunding in two different talks I gave to &lt;a href=&quot;http://yolab.us/possible-futures/&quot;&gt;Intercorp&amp;#39;s new Innovation Lab&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://hastac2014.org&quot;&gt;HASTAC 2014&lt;/a&gt; in Lima. I used it to make the argument that crowdfunding is a process that is rooted in collaborative practices that are common across cultures, and that everything we know about making these practices effective is the raw material of great crowdfunding. For a Peruvian audience, the pollada was a familiar practice that made crowdfunding --- still a relatively new and untested phenomenon in the country --- immediately intuitive. For non-Peruvians, the comparison served to demonstrate the array of socio-cultural precedents that exist for crowdfunding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if the foundations of crowdfunding are deeply rooted, what does that tell us about the future evolution of crowdfunding? What do we know about the way that societies typically organize themselves that might apply to crowdfunding? At Intercorp I argued that there are three key trends emerging in crowdfunding, each of which presents different opportunities for project owners, for platforms, for donors large and small, and for organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crowdfunding is becoming specialized&lt;/strong&gt;. Whereas sites like Kickstarter will let a big range of projects all happen in one place – from films to video games to technology – sometimes you need to connect to people with particular expertise or interest. For example, if you want to attract support for a high-level scientific project, you could use a site like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.experiment.com&quot;&gt;Experiment&lt;/a&gt; to reach the scientific community. Or perhaps you want to reach a niche interest group such as healthcare. &lt;a href=&quot;http://possiblehealth.org&quot;&gt;Nyaya Health&lt;/a&gt; funds medical care for patients in Nepal, seeking funding from around the world. Or perhaps you want to create a public or community service, a process that may require many more steps and legal structures than conventional crowdfunding provides. As I&amp;#39;ve written about frequently on this site and elsewhere, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.civiccrowdfunding.com&quot;&gt;new civic crowdfunding platforms&lt;/a&gt; have emerged to support complex public-private projects like community centers, bikeshare schemes, and public parks. So what is the purpose of specialization? It is an opportunity to isolate and reach a very specific audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crowdfunding is becoming local&lt;/strong&gt;. Organizations in countries outside the US and Europe are making their own platforms. Why? Because local circumstances really matter. For all the apparent ability of the internet to bridge geographic boundaries, a lot of crowdfunding is actually pretty local. There are critical issues like currency and language. But there&amp;#39;s also the challenge of dispersed community building. You need to be able to build a community for your projects, and that’s easier to do if the platform and the community are in a relatively small geographic area. My own research has found that civic crowdfunding campaigns are much more likely to occur in cities where platforms are headquartered. And there are some amazing local crowdfunding examples already. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.catarse.me&quot;&gt;Catarse&lt;/a&gt;, from Brazil, was the first large-scale crowdfunding platform to open source their code. As a result of that – and their talented developers - they’ve been forked by 10 platforms in the US and elsewhere, such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://littlebigmoney.org&quot;&gt;LittleBigMoney&lt;/a&gt; from Colombia, which supports social impact businesses. What this localization of platforms provides is an opportunity to build with a very specific geographic community in mind and to frame the process in a way that is locally intuitive. In Peru, for instance, a pollada-inspired metaphor might seem like a better fit than the `struggling artist&amp;#39; paradigm that is common to Kickstarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crowdfunding is becoming institutional&lt;/strong&gt;. Foundations, corporations or and governments have a lot of experience of and need for fundraising, and now they&amp;#39;re starting to engage with crowdfunding. I described &lt;a href=&quot;http://rodrigodavies.com/blog/2013/10/31/four-models-for-civic-organizations-to-crowdfund.html&quot;&gt;four models of engagement for organizations with respect to crowdfunding&lt;/a&gt;: to be a project promoter, and run projects, to be a curator, and highlight projects that support your goals, to be an investor, and help finance projects directly, or to be a platform, and own the whole process. Each different mode carries with it very different risks and potential rewards, and organizations from startups to municipal governments are experimenting with all of them. This institutionalization of the process is important is that it&amp;#39;s bringing a a lot of new people to the crowdfunding table – to the pollada. And it’s creating new partnerships that cross lines of organizational type, mission and discipline. Those partnerships increase the range and scale of projects that can be crowdfunded dramatically, and hopefully will help recover and regenerate the potential for the public, private and community sectors to work together. Because the best pollada is one to which everyone is invited. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://civic.mit.edu/blog/rodrigodavies/the-digital-pollada-or-what-i-learned-about-crowdfunding-from-peruvian-chicken&quot;&gt;(Cross-posted at civic.mit.edu)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Mon, 28 Apr 2014 10:21:01 -0700</pubDate>
                                <link>http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/04/28/the-digital-pollada-or-what-i-learned-about-crowdfunding-from-peruvian-chicken.html</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/04/28/the-digital-pollada-or-what-i-learned-about-crowdfunding-from-peruvian-chicken.html</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Hawaii Proposes the First Civic Crowdfunding Legislation</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/haw-doe.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hawaii has become the first state to propose a bill supporting civic crowdfunding, as it seeks to raise funds for the maintenance and repair of local schools. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://legiscan.com/HI/bill/HB2631/2014&quot;&gt;HB2631&lt;/a&gt; outlines a pilot program in which two maintenance projects at Hawaii schools are selected for public crowdfunding campaigns. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pilot would be operated by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hawaii3rs.com/about/&quot;&gt;Hawaii 3R&amp;#39;s (Repair, Remode, Restore our Schools)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://projects.propublica.org/nonprofits/organizations/431990722&quot;&gt;a 501(c)(3) organization&lt;/a&gt; started by the late Democratic Senator Daniel Inouye in 2001 to raise private funds to contribute to the backlog in school maintenance projects in Hawaii. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s how it would work, if approved:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hawaii 3R&amp;#39;s selects the two projects for the pilot, in consultation with the Hawaii department of education.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Projects must be &amp;quot;initiated by a member of the community and approved by&amp;quot; the school concerned.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hawaii donates matching funds to Hawaii 3R&amp;#39;s up to a maximum of $50,000 per project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10% of the overall funds raised are donated to a Hawaii school that qualifies for Federal Financial Assistance. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bill, sponsored by sponsored by &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/bethfukumoto&quot;&gt;Beth Fukumoto&lt;/a&gt; (R), Tom Brower (D), Richard Creagan (D), Aaron Ling Johanson (R) and &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/laurencheape&quot;&gt;Lauren Matsumoto&lt;/a&gt; (R), has passed its first reading and has been referred to the education and finance committees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bill does five things that are quite interesting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, it&amp;#39;s the first legislation to use the term &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.civiccrowdfunding.com&quot;&gt;civic crowdfunding&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the proposers are careful to point out that the pilot builds on an existing fundraising mechanism:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Hawaii 3R&amp;#39;s school repair and maintenance fund is an ideal mechanism for a civic crowdfunding pilot program because it already exists to receive private donations for public projects.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The method of bolting crowdfunding onto existing public-private models is a strategy I&amp;#39;ve seen used in many other cases, such &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/80192651/outerlands-parklet?ref=live&quot;&gt;crowdfunded parklets&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ioby.org/project/kips-bay-public-plaza&quot;&gt;Plazas in New York&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#39;s also a welcome reminder that civic crowdfunding is not an entirely new phenomenon, and should be understood in the context of existing public-private fundraising models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, it mandates the superintendent of education to file a report on the performance of the program no later than 20 days prior to the convening of the 2015 session, including &amp;quot;a recommendation on the feasability of using crowdfunding to fund other projects in the department of education and proposed legislation as may be necessary to permanently implement crowdfunding.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourthly, it seeks to have a redistributive effect, by donating 10% of funds raised to a low-income school. The obvious short-run question is &amp;#39;how will that school be selected?&amp;#39; but a bigger question is whether or not blind redistribution at the platform level is the best way to direct civic crowdfunding, and how that strategy would be managed with a larger number of schools involved. It could be argued, for example, that an alternative way to encourage redistribution through crowdfunding would be for the government to offer differential match-funding to schools depending on their socio-economic profile. This would have the added benefit of highlighting the work that is happening in those schools and building a connection between donors and lower-income schools. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fifthly, it doesn&amp;#39;t give either an estimate of the cost (the figure is blank, likely pending finance committee input) or the technical organization of the civic crowdfunding pilot. Will Hawaii use an existing platform, such as Citizinvestor, &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.citizinvestor.com/post/80071292949/civic-crowdfunding-bill-filed-in-hawaii-house-of&quot;&gt;which posted the legislation on its blog&lt;/a&gt;, or will it attempt to &lt;a href=&quot;http://selfstarter.us&quot;&gt;create its own&lt;/a&gt;? &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.donorschoose.org&quot;&gt;DonorsChoose&lt;/a&gt; might wonder why they were not cited as an example given they are by far the most prominent education crowdfunding platform, although the focus on maintenance rather than classroom supplies may mean the DC model isn&amp;#39;t the right fit for Hawaii&amp;#39;s plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m very interested to track the progress of the bill. If you&amp;#39;re familiar with Hawaii&amp;#39;s education system and have thoughts, I&amp;#39;d love to hear from you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://civic.mit.edu/blog/rodrigodavies/hawaii-proposes-the-first-civic-crowdfunding-legislation&quot;&gt;(Cross-posted at civic.mit.edu)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2014 03:21:01 -0700</pubDate>
                                <link>http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/03/24/hawaii-proposes-the-first-civic-crowdfunding-bill.html</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/03/24/hawaii-proposes-the-first-civic-crowdfunding-bill.html</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Is Crowdfunding Participatory Citizenship or a Sign of Institutions in Decline?</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Civic crowdfunding is the beginning of a new type of participatory democracy for communities.&amp;quot;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;quot;Civic crowdfunding is a triumph of individualism over the collective good.&amp;quot;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;quot;Civic crowdfunding is the result of a crisis in government.&amp;quot;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These three divergent intepretations are among the most common responses to civic crowdfunding. I hear them in one form or another almost every time I give a talk on the topic. Despite their differences, these interpretations are also, for the moment, coexisting quite happily. Platforms and the people who use them don&amp;#39;t show much need to agree on what civic crowdfunding is for, or what kind of future its rise might foreshadow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So which one of them most accurately describes what&amp;#39;s actually going on among the people funding civic projects? Earlier this week I presented a paper at the academic conference &lt;a href=&quot;http://clasweb.clas.wayne.edu/citizenship/2014Papers&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Place, (Dis)place and Citizenship&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; at Wayne State University, Detroit, unpacking the framings that we might use to interpret civic crowdfunding and looking closely at recent projects to find out which most closely resembles the dominant discourse around civic crowdfunding. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s how I described the three possible framings of civic crowdfunding: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community Agency&lt;/strong&gt;: that civic crowdfunding is based around collectives, brought together by geographic or interest-based ties, that pool economic and social capital to effect change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Individual Agency&lt;/strong&gt;: that civic crowdfunding is driven by individuals seeking ownership of their environment in an entrepreneurial sense, and reflects the increasing tendency of individuals to bear responsibility and risk previously held by institutions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Institutional Decline&lt;/strong&gt;: that civic crowdfunding is an outgrowth of financial strain among municipalities, and serves a libertarian agenda seeking the reduction of the role of government.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To develop those framings, I analyzed the project pages of 274 campaigns collected from Citizinvestor, IOBY, Neighborly and Spacehive, finding common themes in the language project owners were using. You can hear the full discussion and presentation below, but here&amp;#39;s an overview of what I found in the data: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Place-based community is a very common theme in projects, and is much more frequently invoked than interest-based community&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One in ten projects mentions building a partnership with government to deliver a project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just over one in ten projects cites government financial stress as a motivation or cause&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Entrepreneurial / individual ownership rhetoric seems to be used more often by platform owners than the projects they host&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;#39;t reach a firm conclusion on which of the three framings is most dominant, but the theme of community agency is common enough to be taken seriously, and there is an undercurrent of institutional decline in a significant minority of projects. But it&amp;#39;s clear that crowdfunding is far from unidirectional. What that means is that a lot more qualitative inquiry into how people are using civic crowdfunding and why is necessary to understand its potential and implications for the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an early discussion, and is based on a small subset of the projects I&amp;#39;ve been looking at for my thesis, which will be completed in May. I&amp;#39;m looking forward to sharing a lot more from that resarch here soon. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube.com/embed/qpJwGXAmZQg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://civic.mit.edu/blog/rodrigodavies/is-crowdfunding-participatory-citizenship-or-a-sign-of-institutions-in-decline&quot;&gt;(Cross-posted at civic.mit.edu)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Sun, 23 Mar 2014 03:21:01 -0700</pubDate>
                                <link>http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/03/23/is-civic-crowdfunding-participatory-citizenship-or-a-sign-of-institutions-in-decline.html</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/03/23/is-civic-crowdfunding-participatory-citizenship-or-a-sign-of-institutions-in-decline.html</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>What does it take to win a $10,000 award for Innovation in Crowdfunding?</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/onespark.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
What makes an innovative crowdfunding project? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next month I&amp;#39;m honored to be one of the judges in the Innovation category at the second &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.beonespark.com&quot;&gt;One Spark crowdfunding festival&lt;/a&gt;. As I start to get acquainted with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.beonespark.com/discover/creator_projects?category=innovation&quot;&gt;this year&amp;#39;s finalists&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;#39;m already amazed by the breadth and depth of people&amp;#39;s ideas and ambitions. So how are we possibly going to choose between them? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the approaches I&amp;#39;ll be working with. Many of these thoughts are as much about design thinking or entrepreneurship as they are about crowdfunding, but to me they&amp;#39;re especially relevant when trying to spot innovative crowdfunding campaigns. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first things I look for in a crowdfunding campaign is the question being asked, or the problem at hand that the creators are trying to solve. In some ways inspiring people with a great question or goal is almost more important than showing them a beautiful, finished product. I think this is especially important in the innovation category, and here&amp;#39;s why. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a clear, well-considered question or goal it helps your audience understand that you&amp;#39;re not just bringing them on for a reward – the great product that you&amp;#39;re effectively pre-selling to them – you&amp;#39;re asking for them to join you on a journey. You&amp;#39;re asking them to follow you or your organization while you try and solve a problem or meet a need. That journey might not end as quickly as you expect. It also might not end in exactly the way you expected. What that means is that you have a project that is able to adapt to new circumstances, and backers who are ready to adapt with you. So if your product doesn&amp;#39;t ship as fast you want it to and you have to make some unexpected changes to the design, that&amp;#39;s ok – and it&amp;#39;s ok with your backers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To most people, innovation isn&amp;#39;t about turn-key, off-the-shelf solutions, it&amp;#39;s about figuring out what works by doing it, iterating as you go along. Great campaigns make the case for that kind of work and invite their backers to be a part of the the process. That&amp;#39;s why, when done right, crowdfunding is a great match for innovation projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another quality I&amp;#39;ll be looking for is awareness of the rest of the market. What else has been tried in the space the campaign is operating in, and how is this effort different? That doesn&amp;#39;t mean a campaign needs to list all its potential competitors past and present, but it should have learned from them and be able to distill the most critical improvements into a few sentences. In doing so, the campaign answers an important question: why should this campaign be considered innovative? An innovative campaign shouldn&amp;#39;t have a hard time answering. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m excited to meet this year&amp;#39;s innovation finalists in person next month. Good luck to all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.beonespark.com/blog/what-does-it-take-to-win-the-10-000-innovation-juried-award#sthash.qSEpbDh8.dpuf&quot;&gt;(Cross-posted from the OneSpark blog)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2014 02:21:01 -0700</pubDate>
                                <link>http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/03/17/what-does-it-take-to-win-a-10000-crowdfunding-innovation-award.html</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/03/17/what-does-it-take-to-win-a-10000-crowdfunding-innovation-award.html</guid>
                        </item>
                
                        <item>
                                <title>Introducing the Creative Industries Prototyping Lab</title>
                                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/cipl.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;
Do you know innovators in Latin America? Next month in Lima, Peru, I&amp;#39;ll be co-hosting a three-day workshop for entrepreneurs in the creative industries, focused on design thinking, product development and fundraising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s an exciting project called &lt;a href=&quot;http://yolab.us/cipl&quot;&gt;Creative Industries Prototyping Lab&lt;/a&gt;, and applications to attend the workshop are open now. We&amp;#39;re looking for entrepreneurs who already have the germ of a product or service idea, but are looking to refine their thinking and learn more about how to bring it to market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is that you? &lt;a href=&quot;http://yolab.us/cipl&quot;&gt;Get in touch now&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My five collaborators, &lt;a href=&quot;http://marisca.pe/en/&quot;&gt;Eduardo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://ericadeahl.com&quot;&gt;Erica&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://jasonlipshin.net&quot;&gt;Jason&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pub/julie-fischer/b/328/a7a&quot;&gt;Julie&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/pub/lingyuxiu-zhong/26/433/982&quot;&gt;Ling&lt;/a&gt; and I are interdisciplinary folks drawn from disciplines such as interactive design, research, UX, video games and educational technology, but one of the areas I&amp;#39;m most excited to talk about is alternative fundraising strategies. As regular readers of this blog know, I&amp;#39;ve written often about the &lt;a href=&quot;/2013/09/16/how-to-crowdfund-a-million-dollar-arts-project.html&quot;&gt;risks associated with crowdfunding&lt;/a&gt;, success rates and ways that entrepreneurs are &lt;a href=&quot;/2013/10/17/crowdfunding-as-a-salary-or-crowdfunding-from-your-salary.html&quot;&gt;trying to turn ad-hoc fundraising into a sustainable income stream&lt;/a&gt;. Entrepreneurs in emerging creative industries need to be aware of these issues and possible approaches as they navigate the best way to bring a product to market. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the three days we&amp;#39;ll be holding a series of collaborative and interdisciplinary lectures, workshops and design sessions that lead participants through the potentials and challenges of working in the digital creative industries, and work through a process of critical technology design. Our goal is to produce prototypes of tools, media and processes that allow groups and communities to share creative visions – and to help participants develop the knowledge and skills they need to build audiences, manage community interactions, make an impact on social issues, and develop sustainable creative ventures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CIPL will culminate in a public showcase ahead of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://hastac2014.org&quot;&gt;HASTAC conference&lt;/a&gt;, where you&amp;#39;ll also find several of us giving presentations and papers related to our independent projects. Hope to see you there! &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                                <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2014 03:03:01 -0700</pubDate>
                                <link>http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/03/14/creative-industries-prototyping-lab.html</link>
                                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.rodrigodavies.com/blog/2014/03/14/creative-industries-prototyping-lab.html</guid>
                        </item>
                
        </channel>
</rss>